this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software welcome to software engineering
radio i'm brian red arrow jason Han is a
DevOps champion and an advisor to Victor
ops Jason writes presents and coaches on
the principles and nuance of DevOps
modern incident management practices and
learning from failure Jason is the
author of chat ops managing operations
in group chat which deals with how ops
teams can use group chat to enhance
operation processes and is also author
of an upcoming book entitled post
incident reviews learning from failure
for improved incident response jason is
also a co-host of the community pulse a
podcast on building community within
technology welcome Jason to the show
thanks brian has been great to be a part
of your show despite our best efforts to
deploy quality code on reliable
infrastructure outages still occur and
often it requires human intervention to
restore service having to respond to an
outage critical bug or service
interruption is an inevitable scenario
engineers will face throughout their
careers given the likelihood that we'll
need to respond to an average of some
type I'd like to discuss how we can
prepare ourselves for failures to kick
off the discussion I'd like to ask what
is an incident or outage you know I
think a lot of cases it kind of depends
on the company culture but typically
most organizations especially if they
have IT services that they're relying on
to provide some sort of value to either
an end consumer you know a paying
customer or maybe even just the customer
within the company maybe that's someone
in a different department that IT is
trying to provide services to whenever
there's a disruption in that service
that takes down the ability for those
end users or those consumers to actually
leverage the services and do their work
or get their job done or in the case of
an end user
if they're trying to access let's say a
website or a mobile app and they're not
able to accomplish what's there after
that's typically considered an incident
some something that actually is
disrupting the service that the the
business is trying to provide and
there's a lot of different sort of
models that people use or different
organizations use to sort of determine
the severity of those incidents and what
actually warrants a team responding to
that and and you know dealing with that
so there might be a 71 severity one type
of outage which is a more severe type of
problem or it could be you know
something like i-75 or something lower
where yes something has been disrupted
but there's really no impact to the
end-user maybe something just isn't
behaving like they like they expect but
generally sort of the most widely
accepted sort of definition of that is
are the services and the value that
you're trying to provide to an end-user
being disrupted what kind of outages are
likely to occur in in some cases we
might be deployed on a distributed
system but not always what kinds of
outages are typical that we see you know
usually outages occur when there's been
some sort of recent change you know kind
of one of the jokes we make with with in
sort of the DevOps community is that the
only root cause to an incident or to any
kind of problem really is change and
that's kind of it's two messages there
one there really is no root cause within
these large complex distributed systems
there's a lot of stuff going on all at
the same time and that's just sort of
sort of the nature of these dynamic and
large systems is that they're always
changing and one of the things that many
organizations are doing now is they're
increasing the pace of that change so
they're pushing new features out to
production environments they're making
configuration changes and infrastructure
changes on a very regular routine so
it's usually those changes that they try
to push out into production environments
that cause the initial problem maybe a
bug wasn't caught maybe there was some
sort of load testing that wasn't done
but yeah in a nutshell it's usually
those changes that happen to a
production environment that cause an
outage the second thing
one of the next you know most common
things is going to be really you know
just some sort of failure with a
hardware type of item so maybe a network
switch has gone down or maybe there's
been a power outage so something along
those lines is going to be sort of the
next thing that happens the most and
then another one is just simply humans
you know we make mistakes we cause
problems on our own simply by trying to
improve things trying to just interact
with the software and the systems that
we have and oftentimes we just make a
mistake and cause some sort of problem
and that can even sort of move into
during the remediation phase a lot of
times people recognize that there's a
problem and they go in to try to
understand what's happening and try to
clear up those issues and make them you
know make them better and restore
services but unfortunately a lot of
times they actually end up making things
worse they go in and they they start you
know making changes to different
configuration settings or trying to push
new code out without it being thoroughly
tested and a lot of cases those might
make what was initially sort of a small
impact low severity issue might turn
into a larger one interesting that leads
to another question is how does the
system let you know that there's a
problem how do we discover that there's
an issue should we be actively tracking
the system pulling it on a periodic
basis or is there some other ways that
we become aware of an outage yeah you
know most of the the IT professionals
these days are leveraging some sort of
monitoring service and that could be
something that's agent-based maybe a
software that's running on different
hosts or on different network routers or
whatever but they're able to pull those
different devices or different services
and find out the current status of that
and kind of bring that information back
to a central place so in a lot of cases
those monitoring services as monitoring
tools are the things that actually
detect the problems in the first place
maybe it detects you know there's
there's been a spike in CPU usage or
maybe a hard disk is very close to
filling up that's you know kind of
critical to some sort of key component
to a service but usually and hopefully
they've got some monitoring in place and
a lot a lot of what the DevOps
principles and this whole DevOps
movement has really taught us is that we
want to be captured
that data and have really good
resolution very good telemetry on what's
actually going on with our systems both
hardware
you know virtualized infrastructure
what's going on with the applications
what's happening on the network how
healthy are our databases so there's a
lot of things that really kind of make
up the backbone of a service that a
company's trying to provide and you want
to keep an eye on all that stuff but
then there's also scenarios where you
know maybe an end user or a customer is
the one who notices a problem first and
they'll submit you know maybe a support
ticket or they'll mention something on
Twitter or in some fashion get in touch
with the the organization that's
providing that service and let them know
that they're having trouble and then
hopefully from there you know whoever it
fields that initial ticket or that
support request will then escalate that
onto the teams that can actually begin
the response process and start looking
into what's going on so those are kind
of the main two we hope that you know
businesses are taking their services
very serious and they really do start to
not kind of up their game on the way
that they monitor their infrastructure
and then from you know once you once you
have something keep an eye on your
infrastructure and the applications then
the next piece is really alerting the
right person or right team and get some
eyeballs on it and see if we can start
understanding what the problem is I've
found in some organizations that there's
a failure that it has occurred it goes
unchecked or unnoticed for a long time
and once it has been detected and taken
care of there's a response to that for
avoidance of future problems is to have
a lot of monitoring right to be quite
noisy in the in the modern room that is
to say that I've worked in organizations
that had very noisy alerting systems and
there would be constant notification
alerts probably the thresholds for
alerting were set a little bit too low
with the idea that the hope that it's
better to catch and dismiss than to not
know at all but it had a desensitizing
effect on everybody who was on the alert
list all of the responders how can that
scenario be avoided where we become
desensitized to a noisy system that's a
great point
I mean what you're referring to is you
know what we call just alert
where there's there are so many alerts
coming in and in a lot of cases they're
not actionable they're just letting us
know that you know something appears to
be wrong but if you know an engineer or
someone actually goes in and starts
digging around they realized that this
this really wasn't a critical alert this
this was you know something I'm glad I
know about but I probably didn't need to
be paged for it and so that case where
we become desensitized to these problems
we we actually need to start going in
and tweaking the monitoring services so
that they are only providing actionable
alerts and that's something that's kind
of hard you know for a lot of teams they
kind of consider that technical debt you
know it's something that you know you
need to do but you never quite make the
time or prioritize to go in and start
adjusting those thresholds so that the
person who's on call you know if they're
paged in the middle of the night you
know the last thing you want them to do
is is break you know a good sleep cycle
or something only to discover that there
really wasn't a problem in the first
place that in turn gets engineers kind
of like you're saying where they just
they don't respond as quickly maybe they
don't respond at all so I think that the
key to remember here is that you know
the measurement aspect that that we
understand is very important is
something that has to continuously be
evaluated you really need to go in and
make different tweaks and adjustments
and you know improve the monitoring
tools that we're using to make sure it
really is dialed in and only alerting us
on actionable problems the flip side of
that is that I think with sort of the
proliferation of all of the tools that's
out there monitoring related tools and
of course the shift to the cloud it's
really kind of easy for people to over
monitor and I'm not sure I totally
believe that there is over monitoring I
think there is over alerting in a lot of
cases but I think the real value in
monitoring for the most part comes in
when you're actually trying to dig in to
what's going on or maybe you're doing
some sort of retro the post-incident
review that we were talking about for
the show when you don't have that
information to go dig in and start to
you know understand
what really took place and see if you
can find a trend that makes it hard to
understand how you can improve your
systems in the first place
so I think one of the kind of the key
messages that we hear from a lot of
monitoring companies and specialists in
in this area is that especially with as
cheap as disk space is the true value is
capturing that data not necessarily
trying to alert on it on every single
thing that seems like it might be a
problem but you don't want to not have
that information available to you when
it's time to start digging in so
monitoring can kind of you know provide
two different things first you want to
capture the information so that's there
whether that's a time series database or
something else but you also want to make
sure that the thresholds are adjusted
properly so that if you are gonna page
someone in the middle of the night it
needs to be something that truly is
critical it's actionable something
something really does need to be done
and then there's a whole other you know
list of things and concerns that we need
to make sure if there are gonna page
somebody you want to make sure that they
have the information in the context that
they need to start evaluating what's
happening and you want to make sure that
they have access into the systems that
are having some sort of problem right
now if I'm in being paged and I you know
I'm woken up in the middle of night and
then it turns out I can't even log into
the systems that are that are having
problems that's of no help to anybody so
there's a whole lot of other
conversations to be had
after the monitoring but reducing that
time to detect and that time to know
that there's a problem is definitely one
of them you know one of the early
challenges that a lot of companies have
to figure out listen let's take an
example in the case that you had
mentioned that I might get an alert that
I'm running out of disk space and also
making a quick distinction that
monitoring is of course we're checking
systems were keeping track of maybe
system resources disk disk usage CPU as
you mentioned but then alerting occurs
when those metrics have crossed some
kind of threshold line in the case
that's as an example of running out of
disk space what would be an actionable
that would allow you to take action well
in the case of disk space getting you
know getting large if first of all I
need to make sure that those thresholds
are
are properly dialed in and a lot of that
you have to kind of remember or at least
consider what's driving the maybe the
increase in disk space so for example
maybe on Friday night our systems run a
whole bunch of reports and you know it's
just part of a batch process but there's
a lot of different things happening and
files are being stored and then they'll
be processed and they'll be they'll be
you know kind of cleared out of the
system if I'm being alerted on a bunch
of batch processes that are going to be
cleared out later I I'm gonna have a
problem with that because that's
actually part of our our process is to
use up more disk space simply because
we're trying to run reports and so I
need to keep in mind what's actually
behind you know that disk space usage
but from there when when I if it really
is a legitimate problem it's not like I
was just explaining some sort of
reporting that's happening what the
context that I want to know is is this
something that that has happened over
time did we go from you know 50 percent
disk available to two percent disk
available in about five minutes
or did we get there over the course of
about five weeks because that's gonna
tell me that I have to you know that's
gonna help me understand what kind of
problem I'm dealing with because those
are two very unique scenarios and one
might mean our reports are running and
these will clear out and the other might
mean that we just haven't really been
paying that close attention to our disk
space and now here we are with two
percent left and we really don't even
have enough room to start moving things
around in a safe way so the first thing
I want to know is what's been happening
over time give me that context and then
the next thing I want to know is what
systems or services does this have
potential of impacting and and is it
impacting currently so again it kind of
falls back into what additional pieces
of information can you tell me is this
disk space you know the fact that we're
starting to run out what's the next
Domino or what's the next series of
things that may happen if we don't
respond right now or if we don't start
remediating what's happening so I kind
of I want to understand a clearer
picture about you know what are the
impacts and what's gonna happen
downstream but then I also want to
understanding what what are my options
from here so one of the things that we
advise for epic drops is that when
you're alerted on something there should
be a run book associated with that alert
there should always be something that
tells even the most junior person who
may have just started at the company you
know this week it should tell them where
to start what do you start to look for
and and and how do you access those
systems and which specific commands
should be ran from a command line to
again start digging into actually what's
what's happening and then if you you
know you find that this is the type of
problem that you expected and and here's
what you're supposed to do in the
circumstances what are the next steps
after that so there's a lot of different
stuff but it all kind of can be summed
up into context we really need to know
more about what's happening because an
alert by itself isn't often all that
helpful yeah makes a lot of sense I
think it's worth also mentioning to that
the threshold at which you said your
alerts might be pretty important to
review as well for instance I'd say that
if you've get an alert when you're down
to two percent disk space left it that
might be too late yeah absolutely and
those are things that you know you don't
always stop and realize you need to go
in and adjust those thresholds or you
know maybe if you're tired of being
woken up in the middle of night finally
you're gonna just say hey I'm just gonna
go take care of this even though it's
not part of my normal work it's not it's
not been assigned as as a ticket within
my system it's not part of to you know
this this sprint or anything but I'm I'm
not willing to deal with this anymore
and thankfully the companies that take
their post incident review serious and
they do some kind of retro after an
incident usually the discussion about
what happened will surface those things
so you go through this retro pop process
of understanding what happened and how
did the team respond and what were all
the different metrics that you know came
up and the context that we had or didn't
have then the conversation can start to
switch around to well maybe we should go
into icing or into day to dog or
whatever you know monitoring tool we're
using and start making some changes and
actually schedule and prioritize that
work
otherwise a lot of it just sort of gets
lumped into like I was talking about
earlier with technical debt and you just
you just kind of never get around to it
yeah good point so talking about that
incident review and report there's an
interesting aspect of learning from
failures and I think after an incident
has occurred
sometimes there's maybe a nervousness
about being at blame or maybe sometimes
even the desire to blame and there that
can inhibit a fair discussion of what
happened and learning from the failure
we we talked about learning from system
failures in episode 284 with John all
spa but I want to further that
discussion here how can teams improve
their Incident processes by learning
from previous failures yeah you know the
whole conversation about blameless was
was actually something that I think all
small you know sort of came up with and
turning in and scent in the sense of the
term blameless post-mortems and really
what's behind that is that there are so
many contributing factors to what's
going on both before IT failure and
during the response that when we get
into that retro scenario where we're
coming together as a team and trying to
understand what happened our focus needs
to stay on learning and trying to
understand more about the system
including the how the teams formed and
responded and what they did during the
actual incident as they're recovering
services and the problem with blame
although it's very natural instinct for
all of us it doesn't provide any value
and so you know most of us sort of in
this industry are very guarded about our
time and where we spend our energy and
we weave for the most part have
recognized especially I would say those
kind of paying attention to the DevOps
movement that there's really no room for
blame in fact it actually is more
detrimental than good because if you
create an environment where it's safe
for engineers to discuss what happened
in a very open and genuine and
transparent way then you start to learn
a lot more about what's actually going
on you start to uncover the differences
between work as described and work as
performed you know a lot of a lot of us
kind of know
what should be done but what should be
done and what's actually done are rarely
the same thing and so you want to go in
and actually understand all of that and
when we when we let blame or even you
know different types of bias start to
creep into those conversations it's
actually counterproductive and so I
think that's a big part of the
conversations companies are struggling
with especially large conversations
because there's still a lot of people
within organizations who you know I've
never really been exposed to these types
of ideas or if they have they just
really feel like it had a place in
business you know there's always someone
you wanted to hold accountable for
problems and there's always somebody who
maybe their job was on the line if they
cause some sort of major problem the the
companies that are doing really well
today especially in you know the digital
space and and that kind of stuff are the
ones who actually kind of flipped that
on their head and Etsy is a good example
where we're all small you know was
formerly the CTO over there they had
this sort of neat little thing what they
would do is if an engineer caused some
sort of problem or made problems worse
as they were trying to remediate issues
they were actually awarded this kind of
a fun little prize that they just called
the three armed sweater and and what
that was intended to do was really to
give some attention and some sort of
like recognition to the engineer who is
who's actually exposed something very
very bad within our system so we want to
take this approach where you know people
in humans were fallible we're gonna make
mistakes and what we actually need to do
is find ways for the system to work to
our benefit and work around those
problems and when we introduce blame and
we we start to sort of go down these
paths of counterfactual statements like
well I would have done this if I have
just would have known or I wish I should
have you know when you start using the
woulda coulda shoulda type of language
that right there is a red flag that we
are we're discussing a world that never
happened and never will and it's really
providing no benefit to us and that's
kind of a hard thing for a lot of people
to wrap their head around for for many
reasons I think it's just is human
tendency to want to blame someone and
point a finger at a person when
something doesn't go right yeah blame
you've mentioned it has been can be
counterproductive
what is it what is it preventing us from
getting to the heart of if there's a
either a fear of being blamed or just a
culture of blame what what are we gonna
miss if we concentrate too much on
assigning blame so I think a really
simple example is let's say you know you
were you and I were on an engineering
team together and for whatever reason
you ran a command from from your laptop
on your on your terminal that deleted an
entire database a production database
and it turns out we didn't have any any
backups if if we went in and started
blaming you and and just said hey you
know Brian was responsible for this we
need to make sure Brian four for one he
needs to be removed from this role or
maybe even let go from the company if
he's gonna stick around with us we need
to give him some air you know a lot more
training we probably ought to put some
more process in place and maybe make
sure that this type of thing can't
happen again and so what that does is it
actually like I said you know some teams
will put in new process or they will you
know let somebody go the first problem
with that if you're adding new process
that's really counter to what we're
trying to accomplish through a lot of
the DevOps conversations what we're
actually trying to do is look for
friction in the system and remove that
we want to empower more engineers to
have the tools available to them and the
information and context available to
them so that they're enabled to do the
right thing the second thing is that if
I let you go for making a mistake I then
have to bring someone else in and train
them on how the system works and all
these different you know nuance about
how work gets done around here
when you already knew all that and you
also are now a subject matter expert on
exactly what not to do to delete the
database and you can take that
information and hopefully become sort of
the champion of that and say hey I made
this terrible mistake one time here's
what we've done to try to you know make
it a little bit less of a thing that can
happen but you become that person who
educates the rest of the company or the
rest of the IT or and so there's there's
financial impact if you have to remove
somebody and then bring somebody in and
train them and get them up to speed and
then there's also just you've removed
that opportunity to learn because you've
dismissed this person you've got them
out of the system and all you did was
come up with the fact that it was human
error and that what we're gonna do to
remediate this is actually put in more
process which is counter to everything
DevOps is trying to teach us yeah it
seems that in cases like this no one no
one wants to be the cause of the outage
but if the person is eliminated because
they had been a cause of the outage you
lose the ability for that person to ever
share that experience and teach it to
other people coming aboard and maybe
even prevent future outages by offering
caution and an experience yeah that's a
good point I mean when you incentivize
people to keep their mouth shut
because they're afraid of the you know
the fallout you know maybe you know I
saw I witness Brian being you know let
go for making a very simple mistake that
really anybody could have made now I'm
essentially I'm incentivized to keep
that information close to my chest and
or the information that you know I'm
aware of and like different pieces of
the system and how stuff works and where
there might be blind spots or where
maybe there is access to a system that
you know maybe we shouldn't have
available or there's all kinds of stuff
that engineers discover and and just
becomes part of their you know their
their own knowledge and when we when we
let blame come in there and we we let
people go because of mistakes there's
absolutely no chance of that knowledge
transfer happening there's no way for me
or you to share the lessons we've
learned because we've just slammed the
door on that opportunity and said well
this person made a mistake and so they
gotta go
and so yeah I mean it's a great point
and I think something that a lot of
companies fail to recognize is that
there's actually quite a lot more value
in a very open transparent discussion
about what happened just you know
complete honesty about what happened and
if you can't handle that honesty that's
actually where the problem I think is
yeah for sure
this episode of software engineering
radio is sponsored by data dog data dog
is a monitoring platform that helps
thousands of companies get visibility
into cloud infrastructure optimized
application performance and avoid
downtime data dog integrates with more
than 200 technologies so you can get
immediate insights into all of your
databases your web servers cloud
services and container technologies like
docker and kubernetes start a free trial
today at data dog calm / se radio
let's talk about some diagnostic
techniques let's say that we've gotten
an alert and we know that there is a
problem in the system now we've got to
do some troubleshooting we have to
determine what's failing and how we can
address it we talked about in episode
225 some problem solving methods with
that Brandon Craig I wanted to get your
impression that what do you have a
formal process for diagnosing and
solving system failures as another is
occurring I don't know we have a in
terms of Victor ops I don't know that we
have a formal sort of process I think in
a lot of cases process is a little bit
squishy because we're constantly
improving the way we do things and also
a lot of things that happen are very
unique you know this is the first time
we've ever seen this so if there's any
sort of squishy process at all first of
all it's you know we got to make sure
that we're getting the right people
involved and so there's actually five
sort of full life phases within the the
life cycle of an incident the first
being the detection phase which we've
kind of already went over where you've
got some sort of monitoring in place or
you've got something that will tell you
that there's a problem even if it's a
human that's detected it and then we
move into the response phase which is
actually about getting the right humans
involved in making sure that they have
the context and so this is really kind
of I think the area that we're talking
about right now and it kind of depends
on the makeup of the teams and makeup of
the organization do they have enough
people on their engineering team so that
they can share the load of being on call
you know if engineers have to be on call
you know seven days a week and you know
four months on in
that's actually not beneficial to the
overall value of the service that the
business is providing but if a company
is pretty big then you might be on call
for three days out of a month and and
that's you know that's pretty easy so it
kind of depends on the makeup of the
company in how teams respond but once
they've actually been notified of a
problem the one thing we try to you know
make sure is part of the process is that
they are given that context you know we
want to make sure that there is a run
booked and if there's not
that'll be surfaced in a post instrument
review and we can address that
moving forward but have that had that
context surfaced and then also make sure
that your you always have a secondary so
if I'm the primary person who was paged
I want to make sure that there's a
secondary person on my team who I can
reach out to when and if I need
additional help
so one thing we always make sure is
there's always a primary and secondary
because you never know you know
something will come up in that primary
you just can't get in touch with them
the next thing is that once it's been
established that you know we do have a
problem you want to make you want to try
to understand what's the severity of
this is there customers that are having
impact to this problem is just just a
blip and you know we'll be back online
really quickly but really kind of it's
that whole triaging aspect of the
response phase where we're just trying
to understand what's going on how long
is this gonna you know how are we gonna
be down and try to just get to
understanding more through this
investigative process and then from
there we can move into the remediation
process which again it kind of depends
on the company but we you know maybe you
want to start bringing in additional
resources maybe you need to do sort of
an all-hands-on-deck type of thing and
bringing a lot of people especially if
it's a high severity problem and at
which at that point especially if you
have a larger team it might make sense
for you to establish an incident
commander during that one specific
incident and what I mean by an incident
commander is this is a person who their
role during that incident is really just
to be sort of the traffic cop or you
know somebody to navigate and make sure
that the information is flowing to all
of the different engineers and all the
different stakeholders so everyone's
aware of the same thing and everybody is
working on different aspects of the
problem all in parallel and then coming
back and reporting back into the team
hey this is what I did this is what I
looked at and this is what I saw and so
that again was sharing that information
so multiple engineers can be kind of
investigating in different ways but that
information is all coming back to a
central place it's that incident
commander who kind of manages that
conversation and that communication flow
so I think an incident commander is
often very important especially for
bigger incidents and then once we
- you know deeper part of the
remediation phase I think a lot of it
just has to do with making sure that
systems are accessible and that you've
already hopefully established some sort
of process for people to get into the
systems that they need to you know make
sure that they have the logins and that
they if I need to establish a VPN that
they know how to do that and you know
all of the technical aspects a lot of
that sort of has to be in place or at
least needs to be surfaced during the
incident itself hopefully in a run book
but beyond that you know process of
incident management there's a lot of
folks who kind of follow the you know
the sort of the firefighter type of
mentality of incident management which i
think is very valuable there's a lot of
stuff that is very teachable in there I
think in a lot of cases though the
language within that type of process is
a little bit too command and control
whereas actually we want to empower
individuals to do more to understand the
problem and actually start remediating
the problem but there's a lot of
different ways you can go about it and I
don't I think one of the one of the
benefits but also one of the
frustrations for a lot of organizations
about conversations around DevOps
is that one the processes should always
be improving so we always have to
evaluate them and see is there another
better way to do this and - it's it's
often not prescriptive at all so what
works for us at Victor ops may not work
for you you know so it's really hard
especially when folks and companies come
to me or come to Victor ops for advice
on what's you know what are the quote
best practices for incident management
we'll give them the things that are
working for different organizations and
the things we're hearing about shifts in
the industry but we try to avoid a very
prescriptive approach because honestly
it may not work for their situation so
it sounds like there's actually what
you're describing this is kind of an
incident lifecycle where there's the
first phases are notification of a
problem and then there's trying to
understand characterize the failure or
the incident assignment of people to the
incident and then of course at the once
the remediation is complete maybe taking
a look about what had happened
and figuring out what the cause may have
been for the incident but that life
cycle it's interesting it sounds like
the way that that life cycle is
developed and maybe evolved has a lot to
do with maybe cup of company culture or
the organization's culture it definitely
does we talk to a lot of companies we
have a lot of customers who especially
the enterprise the larger ones who
adhere to IT Service Management sort of
best practices or they follow I tool
they've got a process in place that is
it's there and it's really hard to
change but they they they have to create
a ticket within some sort of you know
service management tooling maybe that's
service now or JIRA or something along
those lines but that's actually an early
step in their process now we argue that
that's that's actually detrimental to to
restoring service because entering in
tickets and all those types of things
that's that's sort of you know that in
our mind the clock is ticking and if
you're not diving right in and or at
least trying to get the right people on
the problem you're you're wasting
precious seconds and I think the average
cost a down time for a lot of companies
is well over $5,000 a minute so the the
extra time that you're you're putting in
to create all these tickets and just you
know go through your process is actually
a harmful and you know affecting the
bottom line of the company and so
there's you know like you were
mentioning the the full lifecycle a lot
of companies they don't really
understand that lifecycle because
because of the processes they have in
place and so when we talk about the
detection phase and then the response
phase and then the remediation phase
oftentimes that's sort of where it ends
for them maybe they will do some sort of
retro but it's really just to try to
identify root cause which I was kind of
joking about earlier
they have a process in place that
probably has been around for years but
nobody's ever stopped to ask is this is
this helping us and can we improve on
this you know on in an almost daily
manner and so the the next phase after
remediation is the analysis phase so
that's where that that post incident
review happens or a post-mortem whatever
language you want to use but you need to
go in and analyze what took place but I
think we're coming
make the biggest mistake is that they do
focus on the cause of the problem rather
than how did we do you know what what
what was the time it took for us to know
about this problem and then did it take
us ten minutes to get you know the right
engineer involved or did it take us
thirty seconds because those are two
different things and they they impact
the cost of that downtime in a large way
and I think unfortunately with the
bigger companies maybe they can sort of
absorb the cost of downtime a little bit
more in some cases but they don't go
into that retro into that analysis phase
looking at it through the lens of how do
we improve our response because to be
perfectly honest you might be able to
prevent something similar to this
problem from happening again
but it's an absolute certainty that
something is going to happen again in
the future and it might look similar to
this it might look completely different
but if you're not going in and talking
about how did we know about this problem
and how did our team come together and
what kind of information was surfaced
and did they have access you know and
all these different things if you're not
really really digging into that then
you're never going to get any better at
responding to problems and that right
there is you know one of the biggest
hang-ups for a lot of folks who are
looking at it-- ESM and i tool and
saying why do we continue to do it this
way when it's been almost proven by you
know sort of the what they call the
unicorns out there the Netflix's the
Amazons the Twitter's that doing this
type of analysis what we're talking
about kind of this blameless mindset and
just really understanding how the teams
formed that's actually causing these
teams to improve you know rapidly and
they're turning their engineers I like
to use the metaphor of a pit-stop crew
you know if you're into racing kind
understand that language that the cars
run around the track all the time and
that's just part of normal operations
that's just part of the system but
eventually something goes wrong they've
run out of gas the tires have been worn
down they've got some sort of you know
fender damage and they need to come in
and fix that stuff and get right back
out on the road that's sort of the new
mentality of a lot of companies is we
got to just know about these problems
quickly and restore them quickly so that
we can get back going we don't
you know create tickets we don't want to
add more process we don't want to blame
people and not understand the system in
a more holistic way so it's that
analysis phase that a lot of companies
kind of skimp out on a little bit they
just focus too much on the root cause
and then the next phase after the
analysis phase is actually the readiness
phase in which we kind of refer to as
well you take all the things that you
learned in your analysis and then you go
back and you improve your systems or
maybe you start performing game days
where you actually intentionally cause
problems in a staging environment or
some other safer environment and just
see how your teams come together and
then talk about that because there's you
know like I said there's there's so many
ways teams can improve the way they
respond to problems but they never
really give them the self to that
opportunity because they focus on the
cause so it's as important to understand
how well you are dealing with problems
as it is to know what the problem
actually was what an outage occurred not
just what failed but are we doing better
about how we respond to failures
absolutely yeah that's a big piece you
know sometimes people just they don't
have the tooling in place or the metrics
in place to sort of expose that but if
they're able to triangulate how long
does it take us to know about the
problem and let's say that's five
minutes well that gives you a number and
some sort of mile marker to try to do
better
gives you an objective well we detected
this problem in about five minutes can
we cut that in half and then the next
phase that took us about 10 minutes or
so 10 to 15 minutes to just get the
right people involved and is there
anything we can do to cut that down you
know and then once we knew what the
problem was and we knew what the impact
was really only took us about a minute
to actually fix the problem and restore
services
unfortunately because we're really good
at engineers and we and once we know
about the problem we and we're sort of
able to grok the issue and what's going
on we can solve it pretty quickly and
that's rarely the problem the problem
lies in actually the time to know and
the time it takes to actually form the
teams and get them diving into what's
going on yeah there's a lot of
interesting stuff there to kind of go
into this a little bit more let's say
that there's an incident occurring right
now and we need to figure out how do we
fun established the severity as we say
what kind of information should we be
looking for that will help us formulate
a hypothesis about what the system is
failing well so I think a lot of it sort
of depends on your business you know
what is it you're providing the first
thing I think a lot of companies do
especially those like yeah you know look
those that are we'll just call the SAS
you know those are providing software as
a service the first thing they'll do is
check how many people did they have
logged into their system right now
because you can hopefully this is
something we didn't touch on but I
probably should have mentioned one of
the other metrics that's very important
to to keep an eye on is stuff that's
related more to the business objectives
so hopefully businesses are keeping an
eye on login requests and session times
and how many people are in the system at
any given time and that establishes a
baseline so if let's say there's some
ABC comm company out there that's got in
general they've got about we'll say a
hundred thousand people in their system
at any given time that's sort of the
baseline if that drops down to just like
a couple hundred people then we know
first of all customers are being
impacted because our logins or our you
know our sessions are way down and so
not only does that tell you that
customers are impacted but it also gives
you a little hint into where you need to
go look because maybe you've your drop
in sockets your you know some sort of
web socket problem and people aren't
able to actually establish a connection
or maybe the login page itself is down
so those types of measurements those
types of metrics are super important but
often overlooked there's stories out
there where really the the service was
operating just fine but they were
running you know it's like an e-commerce
business and for whatever reason they
couldn't process you know American
Express transactions and so to some
people the system is actually perfect
you know hard drives are great the
network's fine memory is all you know
looking good but the fact is that
there's a lot of customers
who could not check out because we
weren't able to accept American Express
and if you're not monitoring for that
you'd never know there's a problem but
that's another major problem
that is actually impacting the bottom
line of the company and so I guess what
the point I'm trying to make here is
that you can start to dig into some of
these really like business focused
metrics to see our customers being
impacted and also that might give you a
little bit of a flag as to something to
go look into like we can see people are
not able to access our services and then
another another good one especially if
we kind of stick with the story of you
know SAS companies we see this all the
time
customers are not afraid to go on social
media especially Twitter and actually
let let it be known that they're having
trouble with that service and so a lot
of companies have to start monitoring
social media and monitoring customer
sentiment and making sure that their
expectations are the customer
expectations are being met and if
they're not then that also gives you a
little bit of insight into where to
start looking for problems yeah
absolutely
one thing I noticed that you mentioned
is baselines and knowing what your
baselines are in in some cases with some
of the teams that I've worked with the
people monitoring or responding to this
happens in smaller companies as well
monitoring systems that they're not
actually really sure what their
baselines are and and the reason that
this happens is in some of these smaller
companies I feel like the the developer
team has worked very very hard to
deliver a Minimum Viable Product and
they reached that point it's launched
but there hasn't been a great deal of
communication between the developers and
the operations team we're going to
support that application in production
and therefore they don't know much about
the application they're supporting or
what is normal behavior how do you break
down that siloed kind of environment
that's a good point and that's really
kind of speaks right to the heart of the
whole DevOps conversation is how do we
how do we dissolve those silos how do we
get the different units within an IT
organization to collaborate and just
work together a little bit better and of
course the DevOps kind of points us to
the developers and the operations are
the ones who really need to you know get
those conversations happening better one
of the sort of we'll just call a concept
within DevOps that is
very prevalent I think really helps
teams understand one approach to this is
this mindset of shifting everything to
the left you know we talk about shifting
security left and shifting quality to
left and and all we really mean by that
is rather than having quality or
operations or whatever team that
traditionally would only be brought in
later in the lifecycle let's bring them
in earlier or let's bring in that that
action or that process so let's do
automated testing in the development
environment or let's bring in you know
the security team and have them sit down
with the developers rather than waiting
until it gets all the way out into a
staging environment and then Security's
like nope that's not gonna work go back
and try again let's move everything to
the left so that we're actually talking
about these things and thinking about
these things much earlier in the process
and one cool sort of a byproduct of that
is that as me as a developer I will then
start to understand the tooling that a
lot of the operations teams kind of
traditionally used a lot of the
monitoring stuff or you know building
out the infrastructure using something
you know some sort of continuous
integration tooling if we start to move
all that to the left and let that be a
part of the developers language and
their toolset then they become a lot
more sort of invested in the service
that they're building or that they're
you know a part of building it also lets
them become a lot more familiar with how
these tools are used and how we can
start monitoring for baselines and
things that are important because as a
developer I have expectations on what it
should do but if I can start to monitor
that earlier on in a scenario that kind
of mimics what it'll look like in a
production environment then I know about
that stuff a lot sooner and I can have
this greater sense of confidence on what
I'm one of my applications supposed to
do you know what's the tool we should be
using to capture metrics should we be
using new relic she'll be using data
dogs some other application performance
tool but your developers become a lot
more familiar and comfortable with that
tooling much earlier in the process and
then one interesting kind of neat thing
about that
is that that opens up the the
possibility of the developers owning
more in production which is something
another you know part of the
conversation with the DevOps is that
people really need to own their the
service that they're building and that
and that doesn't just apply to the
operations teams they're not the ones
who just own production it's really
everyone but it's hard for everyone to
understand it and really feel a sense of
ownership if they don't even understand
the baseline metrics they don't
understand the tooling that's capturing
that metric and how to go in and look at
it so it's kind of like bringing all
these cool tools and ideas and just
moving it all the way to the very
beginning of the lifecycle of creating
software and letting everyone be exposed
to that so that that conversation just
kind of evolves throughout the lifecycle
rather than just getting bolted on at
the end of it would you say that this is
somewhat the function that a site
reliability engineer would provide yeah
absolutely so site reliability
engineering in general is kind of this
focus on obviously the reliability of a
service the availability of a service
but a lot of people you know if you
start to talk about what a site
reliability engineer does as a specific
role a lot of it just is kind of
bringing these concepts these DevOps
content concepts bringing them in and
and sort of sprinkling them around
throughout the different different teams
within within the IT or
and with again sort of having this lens
of when we sit down to start writing
code I'm going to as an SRE I'm gonna
sit down with my developer and I'm gonna
make sure that one they're aware of all
the tooling that's out there that we
could use to you know create those
baseline metrics and monitor the things
that are important but also they start
having conversations with the developers
about things like scalability and what's
gonna happen if we go from 10,000 users
to a hundred thousand users is the way
you're designing this piece of the
application or the piece of the service
is it gonna hold up for that because if
it's not then then we need to rethink
how we're doing this and so the site
reliability engineers in a lot of cases
it's it's a software developer who
understands a lot of the operations type
of work in other cases it's an operation
person who has suddenly had this strong
desire to start playing around with more
automation and some of the things that
are more or have traditionally been more
exposed to just the developer so it's
kind of a blend of both software
development and the operations teams
where people come together or you know
one person will kind of bring those two
aspects together and then kind of I
guess disseminate that knowledge
throughout the entire IT org so that as
they are building the service they're
actually thinking more about how this is
going to look in the future how are we
going to scale this should we be looking
into containers what are some of the
friction points in our delivery pipeline
they start to introduce language like
value stream maps and lots of really
kind of interesting ideas that are
really just intended to both break down
the silos remove friction in the system
but also get everyone on the same page
about what are we trying to accomplish
here and how do we all own this together
with this person who cited reliability
and Jerry also frequently be the
incident lead for incidents that require
group organization I think it kind of
depends on the makeup of the company I
think in a lot of cases you're right
that is that does end up being the role
of a site reliability engineer during
some sort of major incident they can
sort of play that that middleman that
incident commander but again like I
mentioned earlier there's really no
prescriptive approach to it but the fact
that that person likely has a pretty
rounded knowledge of the system and
different ways to approach it they they
can be very beneficial being sort of
that middleman requesting you know
developers go go look into this and
security go check out what's going on
over here and operations team I need you
to go look at this especially if the
team really hasn't already kind of come
together and and they're already
building that knowledge transfer and
starting to all kind of understand and
have better awareness the sre can sort
of be that bridge in the middle that
starts to get all those teams working a
lot better together especially during an
incident so incidence of course don't
happen in a vacuum
there
there's usually as you had mentioned
there's a loss of business availability
and a lot of what we need to do in
addition to diagnosing and addressing
the issues is that we need to message
the status with stakeholders business
stakeholders and when there's an outage
the the thing that those business
stakeholders seem to be most interested
in is when will the service be back up a
little service be restored how can we
provide reasonable estimates for time to
recovery one thing I want to point out
is that you're totally right in that
there are a number of stakeholders that
are gonna want to know what's going on
especially leadership they you know they
really in those cases don't always care
about the specifics of the problem they
just want to know how long they're going
to be down when is everything going to
be restored and so there are tools out
there status pages that type of thing
that are really intended to sort of
cross that that bridge or get those
people notified about what's going on
and so companies that follow kind of
these modern incident management
practices
they'll have engineers or maybe it's the
incident commander go in and update a
status page as soon as they have new
relevant information so that they're
constantly sort of sharing this
information one of another big thing
about DevOps is that they're always
sharing they're being very transparent
about what's going on and the
stakeholders aren't always going to be
just the leadership team or the people
within the company stakeholders are also
going to be the customers and so they'll
leverage things like Status pages or
even social media and of course you know
sending out emails to customers to sort
of update them on what's happening but
oftentimes it's really difficult to know
when service is going to be restored so
I think that kind of speaks to why
transparency has become sort of a very
strong term I guess within DevOps is
that if me as an engineer I'm working as
hard as I can to solve the problem but I
still don't quite have an idea of when
it's going to be restored I need to
communicate that and I need to let
people know what's happening so there's
there's been a number of actually kind
of major outage outages Amazon's s3 last
year there was a major DNS problem also
last year there's you know a number
sort of big incidents and outages that
kind of made media this year or last
year and almost all of them they never
really know how long it's gonna take but
what they did a pretty good job about is
actually keeping the public or keeping
their stakeholders engaged and up to
date with what they know what they're
looking into you know and as things
change they keep them all up to date in
a very kind of continuous and repetitive
way so that me as an end user of
Amazon's s3 I'm not just sitting around
without any kind of information I'm
actually being updated on a pretty
regular cadence and that gives me some
sort of comfort that hey they're doing
something and they're probably doing it
as quickly as they can but at least
they're not just sitting on their hands
saying we don't know what's going on
yeah I imagine sometimes it can be
difficult not not being able to say when
you expect to have service restored I
found that difficult sometimes to
articulate that we're working hard on it
but we don't have an estimate just yet
we're still in that diagnosis phase yeah
I think if you're still if you haven't
gotten to the remediation phase of the
incident if you're still in that
response phase where you're triaging
you're investigating you're just trying
to understand what's going on there's no
way for you to really know it's not
until you get into the remediation phase
where you're actually taking action and
let's say I've discovered you know that
you know we just found there was a major
bug but that's that's what's causing the
problem well we discovered the bug we've
now corrected the bug in our development
environment and now it's going through
all of our automated testing get through
staging and then get to you know all the
different requirements before it gets
into production at that point hopefully
because I'm pretty familiar with the
delivery pipeline I'm pretty comfortable
in terms of how long does this process
take I as an incident commander or
whoever might go in and update that
status page that's exactly what I'm
gonna tell my stakeholders we've
discovered a bug it has been corrected
in our staging environment and it's
going through all of its automated
quality testing and it should be out in
you know X number of minutes but unless
you have the confidence in your own
release process and what your delivery
pipeline looks like and a lot of it's
already kind of automated so you have a
very very we'll just say close estimate
on on how long it takes to get your code
from development staging and then into
production
it's really difficult for you to give
any kind of accurate updates now from
time to time we may have to deal with
someone like a customer or maybe a
business stakeholder who's irate or
emotional or upset or frustrated how can
we handle the kind of communication or
interaction with someone who is us at
and and we're under stress we're trying
to diagnose a problem any best practices
with dealing with people that are upset
or angry well I think in a lot of cases
you know people are rightly upset
especially if let's say I'm a business
who's providing some sort of API access
into my system and another business is
relying on that API access and the
services for their business my outage
may be causing their outage or at least
affecting their bottom line so they're
rightfully upset about what's happening
I think what we were just talking about
the transparency is your is your biggest
ally letting the stakeholder letting
whoever is upset let them know exactly
what's happening let them know that we
detected a problem it was at this time
we've got engineers we've got our best
people looking at it we'll update you as
quickly as we can just being honest with
them and being transparent about the
process that you have in place is your
first step the next one is if that
person continues to come in and be
disruptive to the actual remediation
process and there needs to be someone
whether that's the incident commander or
you know somebody else on the team needs
to be able to step in and sort of you
know be the umbrella of the engineers
and just let them continue their work
because the one of the worst things or
one of the most detrimental things to
recovering from a problem is shoulder
tapping and context switching and people
coming in and asking for updates what's
going on give me an update tell me
you're gonna have it up you know you're
gonna have things working in the next
few minutes that's actually detrimental
to recovering services so I think
sometimes in some cases you do need to
have a person who can kind of run
interference between internal
stakeholders to make sure they're not
actually slowing down the process that
it's required to actually understand and
recover from a problem in a lot of cases
you know that that could be the incident
commander it could be a senior engineer
it could be somebody else on the
leadership team understanding that
they're working as quickly as they
can will they're gonna update us every
time that there is something important
to share and we just need to be patient
because that's our quickest path to
recovery so often the cases that support
engineers or engineers who are on pager
duty frequently or on schedule they'll
develop the most in-depth experience and
expertise with the system oftentimes
hard-won they're also the ones that are
probably at the highest risk for burnout
what can we do to prevent attrition of
these experienced engineers burnout is
you know one of the hardest things about
incident management I think especially
for for teams who aren't able to really
share the load you know bring more
developers on call and and establish
some sort of escalation path and maybe
some rotations so that people aren't on
call the time it happens all the time we
hear people who just decide they don't
want to be an OPS anymore they decide
they don't want to be in software
anymore because they they've just had to
respond to many problems and so what we
usually a sort of advise companies is to
start tracking you know let's let's make
data-driven decisions here about even
our on-call best practices let's make
sure that if we've got a system that we
want to maintain high availability for
that we take that very serious and we
don't just dump it on one person or just
a couple of people because that's not
sustainable no matter who the engineer
is and how talented they are and what
kind of information that they hold in
their head it's just not it's not
sustainable and it's furthermore it's
not humane and you know that's another
big conversation of the DevOps sort of
movement is that on-call practices need
to be humane you can't page people after
hours for things that aren't actionable
you can't expect engineers to be on-call
you know 20 days out of a month you
can't expect people to you know have to
miss their children's birthdays you
can't expect people to not take vacation
there that's just not it's not a
long-term sustainable plan and so we try
to educate companies and teams on
tracking metrics how long are people on
call you know over the course of a month
or a week or whatever how many incidents
are they dealing with in that time
because a lot of that if they're on call
for a week and they only got paged one
time that's that doesn't you know sound
too bad but they got paged everything
day that's going to take a toll on
someone so start paying attention to the
metrics that are involved with your
infrastructure and then once you have
those metrics but the other big piece is
during your host incident review during
that analysis phase let's talk about
what's going on with those engineers who
was paged and how long have they been on
call because if I'm the one who was
paged and it took me ten minutes to
respond that's a little bit excessive
that's a little bit too much but if it
turns out that during the discussion of
that incident we can surface well
Jason's been on call for 15 days
straight that helps me understand why it
took 10 minutes for him to respond you
know he's he's had to deal with this
he's the lone person responsible for
responding to these problems for way too
long we've got to shift some of this
responsibility around so I guess the
short answer to that is that you know
you can start making data-driven
decisions on your on-call rotations and
and who's gonna be responsible for what
and how many days should they be on-call
in a row and you and you know you just
start to make smart decisions rather
than just saying well you're in an ops
or you're an SRE so you're responsible
for being on-call that's not the path to
high availability and reliability that's
the path to burnout I imagine that it's
probably worth reminding engineers who
wish to be helpful don't force yourself
to be a hero take down time don't always
respond to everything that's outside of
your your support rotation yeah that's a
great point hero culture is one of the
probably the biggest harming kind of
notions within within IT you know we
really don't want heroes we don't want
the ninjas we don't want rock stars we
don't want any of that we want we want
humans who are good at what they do and
we're gonna treat them very well and and
we're gonna let them you know be
empowered to make the right decision
we're gonna give them all the tools and
and what they need to do their job but
at the end of the day you know we can't
we can't burn out our people we've got
to make sure that they do their best job
but we don't set expectations that are
just too high and not attainable yeah
well thank you very much Jason just a
quick question on your new
post-incident reviews learning from
failure and improved Incident Response
is that now published it is yeah we just
we just released that I guess it was
week and a half ago or so it's available
for digital download currently and I can
give you a URL for that and then
hopefully we'll have physical books here
from the publisher within the next week
or so definitely by the end of or by the
middle of August I'm told terrific
well thank you so much for joining us
thank you this has been great good to
talk to you Brian
good to talk to you too this has been
Brian De Niro for software engineering
radio thanks for listening to Nessie
radio an educational program brought to
you by Archer police software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at SE -
radio net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of se Radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening